{"tossups": [{"question": "This modern-day country was outraged by the Council of Blood being imposed as its ruler, as well as by the Tenth Penny tax. It allied with the \"Sea Beggars\" against Spanish governors such as the Duke of Alba and won its independence in the Eighty Years War. For 10 points, name this country where William the Silent reigned over land reclaimed from the sea via dikes.", "answer": "the <b><u>Netherlands</u></b> [or <b><u>Holland</u></b>; or the <b><u>United Provinces</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This woman was implicated in a fraud known as the Affair of the Diamond Necklace. She became known as \"the widow Capet\" following the death of her husband, Louis XVI. For 10 points, name this queen of France who legendarily dismissed a crowd of peasants crying out for bread by saying \"let them eat cake.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Marie Antoinette</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "These people believed that people who died by drowning went to an underworld ruled by Tlaloc (<b>pr. tuh-LAH-lock</b>) rather than the main underworld, Mictlan (<b>pr. MIKT-lon</b>). These people believed that an eagle with a snake in its mouth had alighted on a cactus, telling them where to build their capital. For 10 points, name this group that worshipped Quetzalcoatl (<b>pr. KET-sul-coh-AH-tul</b>).", "answer": "<b><u>Aztec</u></b>s", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "A sculpture group by this artist depicts an incident in which Eustache de Saint Pierre led six men into captivity in 1347 following a battle with Edward III. The most iconic piece by this sculptor was part of his exhibition <em>The Gates of Hell</em> and represents Dante planning the <em>Divine</em> <em>Comedy.</em> For 10 points, name this sculptor of <em>The Burghers of Calais</em> and <em>The Thinker.</em>", "answer": "Auguste <b><u>Rodin</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This industry became involved in a scandal during the Spanish-American War when it supplied poor-quality goods to Nelson Miles's troops in Puerto Rico. This industry was later fictionalized as mistreating immigrant Jurgis Rudkus, leading Theodore Roosevelt to support the Pure Food and Drug Act. For 10 points, name this industry which Upton Sinclair targeted in <em>The</em> <em>Jungle</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>meat</u></b>packing industry", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Two sports teams based in this country met in the Naismith Cup. In 1993, a team based in this country employed John Olerud and Paul Molitor. This country's lesser-known national sport is lacrosse, and its football league contests the Grey Cup every year. For 10 points, name this former home of the NBA's Grizzlies and current home of baseball's Blue Jays.", "answer": "<b><u>Canada</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man personally financed and organized a rescue mission for employees of Electronic Data Systems who were imprisoned in Iran. He chose James Stockdale as his running mate in a Presidential election that saw him widely mocked for buying network airtime to display a series of charts. For 10 points, name this independent who received twenty percent of the vote in 1992.", "answer": "H. Ross <b><u>Perot</u></b> [Hiram Ross <b><u>Perot</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Emmanuel Timoni first described a method of preventing this disease, which Mary Worley Montagu famously was guarded against in Constantinople. Cotton Mather wrote in support of inoculation against this disease, which was proved feasible in England by Edward Jenner. For 10 points, name this formerly devastating disease which was eliminated by the 1990s.", "answer": "<b><u>smallpox</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The chief justice during this event, William Stoughton, controversially allowed \"spectral evidence\" to be introduced, an action later condemned by Increase Mather. These events began with accusations against the slave Tituba and resulted in dozens of executions by hanging and pressing. For 10 points, name this episode of mass hysteria in 1692 Massachusetts.", "answer": "<b><u>Salem witch trials</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Much of the groundwork for this institution was laid at the San Francisco Conference by spy Alger Hiss. At this institution, Valerian Zorin was told \u201cdon\u2019t wait for the translation\u201d by Adlai Stevenson, who served as U.S. ambassador to this institution under John F. Kennedy. For 10 points, name this successor to the League of Nations which meets in New York.", "answer": "the <b><u>UN</u></b> [<b><u>United Nations</u></b>]  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 6 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When setting up skeletons of this species for display, museums frequently used the skull of <em>Camarasaurus</em>. That practice perpetuated Othniel Charles Marsh's belief that this species was not identical to a skeleton unearthed in 1885. For 10 points, identify this dinosaur species which Marsh erroneously identified as separate from the fictitious \"brontosaurus.\"", "answer": "<b><u>apatosaurus</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {}, {"question": "This man hid out at Liliesleaf Farm after the Treason Trial, where he organized the militant group Spear of the Nation. He gave the \"I Am Prepared to Die\" speech at the Rivonia Trial, which led to his lengthy imprisonment on Robben Island. For 10 points, name this man who ultimately worked with F.W. de Klerk to end the apartheid system in South Africa.", "answer": "Nelson Rolihlahla <b><u>Mandela</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Jacob Bernoulli discovered that this number is the \"force of interest,\" the limit of the interest accruable on a dollar by increasing the frequency of compounding. A 1727 paper on the explosive force of cannons introduced this number as the base of the natural logarithm. For 10 points, identify this mathematical constant named for its Swiss popularizer.", "answer": "<b><u>e</u></b> [or <b><u>Euler's number</u></b>; or <b><u>Euler's constant</u></b>]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {"question": "This composer incorporated \"Springfield Mountain\" and \"Camptown Races,\" along with excerpts from the Gettysburg Address, into his World War II patriotic piece <em>A Lincoln Portrait.</em> He scored ballets about Billy the Kid and about pioneers building a farmhouse in western Pennsylvania. For 10 points, name this composer of <em>Appalachian Spring.</em>", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Copland</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This device was originally named for doctor Antoine Louis. The \"tricoteuse\" (<b>pr. TRICK-aw-tooz</b>) were women who knitted next to this object. This object was used on up to forty thousand people at the order of Maximilien Robespierre, who found himself subject to it in 1794. For 10 points, name this item which was used to execute Louis XVI and others during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b><u>guillotine</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This system was restored following the overthrow of Hippias (<b>pr. HIP-ee-uss</b>), after which its central feature was the boul\u00e9 (<b>pr. BOO-lay</b>). This system involved citizens being arranged into demes (<b>pr. DEEMZ</b>) by Cleisthenes (<b>pr. CLICE-thuh-neez</b>). For 10 points, identify this political system used in classical Athens, which inspired similar vote-based systems in the modern world.", "answer": "Athenian <b><u>democracy</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This language was used to write <em>The Incoherence of the Philosophers</em>, which was rebutted with <em>The Incoherence of the Incoherence.</em> This was the language used by the medieval philosopher Averroes (<b>pr. AA-vuh-ROE-ez</b>) and other writers based at C\u00f3rdoba (<b>pr. CORE-doh-buh</b>). For 10 points, name this language through which many Greek and Latin texts passed to Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Arabic</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "In the twentieth century, some groups modified this holiday to use a \"cup of Miriam\" to symbolize women and an orange to symbolize homosexuals. This holiday also changed in the twelfth century, when its service was collected as the \"haggadah\" (<b>pr. hah-GUH-duh</b>). For 10 points, name this Jewish holiday on which the \"seder\" (<b>pr. SAY-dur</b>) meal includes matzah (MAHT-suh).", "answer": "<b><u>Passover</u></b> [or <b><u>Pesach</u></b>]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Letters leaked by Henry Simpson McComb first exposed this company's actions to the</u></b> <em><b><u>New York Sun</u></b></em><b><u>. This company was organized by George Train and Thomas (+)</u> Durant, and it began a cozy relationship with Congress following the installation of Oakes (*)</b> Ames as its president. It held an inflated contract with the Union Pacific railroad. For 10 points, name this company at the center of an 1872 Grant administration scandal involving political graft.", "answer": "<b><u>Credit Mobilier</u></b> of America", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A succession war named for this area began on the death of Maximilian Joseph in 1777</u></b> <b><u>and was also known as the \"potato war.\" Motifs from Wagner (</u></b><u>pr. VOG-ner</u><b><u>) operas are</u></b> <b><u>used to decorate the (+)</u> Neuschwanstein (</b>pr. noy-SHVON-shtine<b>) Castle in this region, which was built by its (*) </b>\"Mad\" king Ludwig II. For 10 points, name this southeastern German state and historic kingdom, where many German Catholics and the city of Munich can be found.", "answer": "<b><u>Bavaria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The protagonist of this TV show insisted that if Ronald Reagan dyed his hair, he only did</u></b> <b><u>so \"to show his strength to the Communists,\" and had his faith in the Republican Party</u></b> <b><u>tested when he discovered that (+)</u> George W. Bush had a limp handshake. An episode of this show is about a plot to steal Santa Anna's (*)</b> wooden leg on its way back to Mexico, and in another, former governor Ann Richards dates Bill. For 10 points, name this former FOX cartoon about Arlen, Texas.", "answer": "<em><b><u>King of the Hill</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These places grew up after World War II on the \"Levittown\" model. These places were</u></b> <b><u>the destination of \"white flight,\" and attempts to combine their (+)</u> school systems with majority-black districts in the 1970s led to \"busing\" programs. The automotive dependence of these places is criticized for contributing to (*)</b> \"sprawl.\" For 10 points, name these places to which middle-class Americans shifted after the 1950s, from which many people commute to cities.", "answer": "<b><u>suburb</u></b>s (prompt on \u201cexurbs\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This movement's victory was secured at the Battle of Verti\u00e8res (</u></b><u>pr. VAIR-tee-air</u><b><u>). This</u></b> <b><u>movement was started by the \"houngan\"</u><u>Dutty Boukman, and it was partially betrayed to</u></b> <b><u>Charles (+)</u> Leclerc. Following this movement's success, its victors immediately split into factions supporting either Henri (*)</b> Christophe or Jean-Jacques Dessalines. For 10 points, name this successful slave rebellion which was initially led by Toussaint L'Ouverture (<b>pr. TOO-sahn ver-TOR</b>).", "answer": "<b><u>Haitian revolution</u></b> [or descriptive answers such as <b><u>slave revolt in Haiti</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These items may have been named for the shipworkers on Hog Island who enjoyed them</u></b> <b><u>in the Philadelphia area. Another name for these items is attributed to Dominic Conti, who</u></b> <b><u>took inspiration from viewing the (+)</u></b> <em><b>Fenian Ram </b></em><b>on display in a museum. Less certain origins for this object\u2019s names include the New England term (*)</b> \u201cgrinder\u201d and the New York area \u201chero.\u201d For 10 points, name this lunch food popularized by Italian-Americans and now served as a \u201cfive-dollar footlong.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>sub</u></b>s [or <b><u>hoagie</u></b>s; or <b><u>grinder</u></b>s until it is read; or <b><u>hero</u></b>s until it is read; or <b><u>submarine</u> </b>sandwiches; or any other regional term; prompt on <b><u>sandwich</u></b>es]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man coined the name \"scissors crisis\" during the period of the New Economic</u></b> <b><u>Policy. He also created the term \"degenerated workers state\" to summarize his views on</u></b> <b><u>what the (+)</u> Soviet Union became following his deposition as head of the Red Army. He was ultimately killed in (*)</b> Mexico by Ramon Mercador. For 10 points, name this member of the Left Opposition who was outmaneuvered by Joseph Stalin for leadership of the USSR.", "answer": "Leon <b><u>Trotsky</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Frank Morris and the Anglin brothers left fake heads behind at this location in 1962.</u></b> <b><u>From 1969 to 1971, this location was occupied in a political protest by the Indians of All</u></b> <b><u>Tribes. Burt (+)</u> Lancaster played the title role in a film about Robert Stroud, the \"birdman\" of this place. Officially, no one ever (*)</b> escaped from this place, assuming Morris and Anglin drowned before reaching Angel Island. For 10 points, name this former prison and island off San Francisco.", "answer": "<b><u>Alcatraz</u></b>  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 6 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras ONLY READ IF A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER IS NEEDED! </b> <b><u>This king was the beneficiary of the original Act of Supremacy. He raised funds for the</u></b> <b><u>middle part of his reign by dissolving nearly all monasteries in his kingdom, with the</u></b> <b><u>assistance of his first administrator Thomas (+)</u> Wolsey. This king was the father of Edward VI, (*)</b> Mary I, and Elizabeth I. For 10 points, name this king whose attempt to divorce Catherine of Aragon triggered the English Reformation and his five subsequent marriages.  ANSWER: <b><u>Henry VIII</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Henry</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}